<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE faqs SYSTEM "docs.dtd">
<faqs title="Pentagram" changed="30 October 2011 (GMT)">
	<section title="Introduction">
		<sub name="pent_is">
			<header>What is <Pent/>?</header>
			<body><para>
				<Pent/> is a game engine for running Ultima 8 on modern 
				operating systems. Since a modified version of the 
				Ultima 8 engine also powered the two Crusader games 
				(Crusader: No Remorse and Crusader: No Regret) our ultimate 
				goal is to be able to run those two as well. Right now 
				we don't support them but you will be the first to know 
				when we do.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="name_origin">
			<header>Why is it called <Pent/> - are you satanists or something?</header>
			<body><para>
				If you ever played Ultima 8 or bought the first release of the game,
				then you will have noticed the big pentagram on the game box and the
				intro. That is the sole reason for this name.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="donations">
			<header>Do you accept donations?</header>
			<body><para>
				No, the <Pent/> team will not accept donations. For us there 
				are greater legal matters involved, which none of us 
				particularly want to explore. We do not want to risk the wrath 
				of EA for directly profiting from <Pent/>. If you want to donate 
				to anyone, donate to Sourceforge. We wouldn't be here if it 
				weren't for them.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="origin_support">
			<header>Does Origin support <Pent/>?</header>
			<body><para>
				First of all, Origin has been owned by EA for a long time now and 
				from recent developments it seems that Origin only exists now to 
				maintain Ultima Online. Furthermore since we have never managed to make 
				contact with EA or Origin while working on Exult we didn't even try 
				to contact them this time. So, no, Origin and EA do not support 
				<Pent/> and will most likely just ignore questions about us.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="support_Ultimas">
			<header>Will <Pent/> support other Ultimas?</header>
			<body><para>
				No. All Ultimas are so different it wouldn't make sense to support 
				them with the <Pent/> engine. However, for most Ultimas engines are 
				being developed similar to <Pent/>.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="multiplayer">
			<header>Will <Pent/> ever be multiplayer?</header>
			<body><para>
				There are no plans to ever make <Pent/> a multiplayer engine, and it 
				really wouldn't make sense for Ultima 8 to be played by more than one 
				person.<br/>
				However, a deathmatch scenario for the Crusader games would be fun (in 
				Dominus' opinion at least) and once we support these two games, people 
				are welcome to develop a multiplayer version.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="dl_pent">
			<header>Where can you download <Pent/>?</header>
			<body><para>
				Daily SVN snapshot binaries for Windows (by Travis Howell), Mac OS X (by Dominus) and the SVN 
				snapshot source tree can be found at 
				<extref target="http://pentagram.sourceforge.net/download.php"/>.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="snapshot">
			<header>Binary, snapshot, source tree - what are you talking about?</header>
			<body><para>
				First of all, if you are running Windows and you just want to run/play 
				<Pent/>, download the SVN Snapshot binary called 
				<strong>Windows Binary</strong>.
			</para><para>
				Source is the code of Pentagram and is only useful for programmers that 
				want to look at it, compile it or, hopefully, want to contribute to the 
				project. Once you compile the code you get a binary or in other words 
				the actual program.<br/>
				SVN snapshots are the newest source code. Whenever
				we change some code, Travis and Dominus make a new snapshot the next day. 
				As we currently have no releases, snapshots are the only way for you to
				run <Pent/>.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="old_snapshot">
			<header>And what is that old snapshot supposed to be?</header>
			<body><para>
				For that you'll have to take a look at <Pent/>'s history.<br/> 
				The project started out as a pet project by some of the Exult programmers. 
				We tried to figure out the various file formats and used a sub tree of the 
				Exult source code space. For example we developed a map viewer, a shapes 
				viewer (shapes are the graphic files of Ultima 8) and many other tools.<br/>
				Only when the code of <Pent/> became more mature we decided to make it a 
				separate project. The code developed so far was taken over to the new project 
				space as the "old" module but we still worked on it.<br/>
				Since the code that was written was meant for small viewer programs and not 
				for a full game engine, we decided to start from scratch on <Pent/> itself.
			</para><para>
				Some of the tools in the old snapshot are not yet ported over to the actual 
				Pentagram code and therefore users and programmers might find it still useful. 
				A listing of the tools follows.
			</para><ul>
				<li><strong>unpackshp</strong><br/>
				The most useful tool now. If you don't have u8shapes.flx in the static 
				subdirectory, you have to use this tool on u8shapes.cmp to have it decompressed.
				</li>
				<li><strong>dcmpsound</strong><br/>
				Sound and Voice effects in Ultima 8 were compressed with Sonarc. Dcmpsound uses 
				u8.exe of the original game to decompress the sfx into something we can use. 
				For dcmpsound to find u8.exe and the sfx flex files you have to edit 
				pentagram.cfg.
				</li>
				<li><strong>dcmpsound2</strong><br/>
				Same purpose as dcmpsound, only it doesn't use u8.exe to decompress the sfx.
				</li>
				<li><strong>u8extract</strong><br/>
				Extracts the archives Ultima 8 used to store its files. Their file ending is 
				.flx and they are called flex files.
				</li>
				<li><strong>u8savextract</strong><br/>
				Used to extract savegames. The initial game is also a savegame and to actually 
				start the game we needed to figure the savegame format out. And no, apart from 
				the initial savegame, you can't run other savegames from the original.
				</li>
				<li><strong>dequote</strong><br/>
				Shows you the content of the quotes files (quotes.dat and ecredit.dat).
				</li>
				<li><strong>shpdisp</strong><br/>
				Lets you browse through the graphics of the game. See the readme that comes with 
				it for more details.
				</li>
				<li><strong>animdisp</strong><br/>
				Lets you browse through the animations of the game. See the readme that comes with 
				it for more details.
				</li>
				<li><strong>globdisp</strong><br/>
				Lets you browse through the globs of the game. See the readme that comes with it 
				for more details.
				</li>
				<li><strong>mapdisp</strong><br/>
				Lets you browse through the maps of the game. See the readme that comes with it for 
				more details.
				</li>
			</ul></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="no_release">
			<header>Why has there not been a release yet?</header>
			<body><para>
				<Pent/> is not yet in a state we want to officially release. Whenever we do feel 
				like <Pent/> is ready we will make an official release.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
	</section>
	<section title="Ultima 8: Pagan">
		<sub name="need_u8">
			<header>Do I need Ultima 8?</header>
			<body><para>
				Yes, without the original files you can't play Ultima 8 with <Pent/>.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="u8_playable">
			<header>Is Ultima 8 playable?</header>
			<body><para>
				Yes and no. Most of the plot works and several people have managed to 
				play through Ultima 8 already. However, there are many things not yet
				fully working.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="u8_versions">
			<header>Does <Pent/> work with all versions of Ultima 8?</header>
			<body><para>
				Ultima 8 was released in English, French, German, Spanish and Japanese.
				All five should run in <Pent/>, but the non-English versions,
				especially the Japanese version, need much more testing.
			</para><para>
				On a side note, we heard that the Spanish version might not have been actually finishable. At 
				some point in the game you are supposed to get the Tear of Seas from Devon but the 
				conversation option might not be there.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="lost_vale2">
			<header>Will the Lost Vale run on <Pent/>?</header>
			<body><para>
				Unfortunately the add-on for Ultima 8, called the Lost Vale was never released. 
				Rumor has it that it was actually finished but Origin/EA decided there was no 
				market for it and lost it.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="old_saves">
			<header>Do save games from the original work in <Pent/>?</header>
			<body><para>
				No. Although we did figure out the savegame format and are able to run the initial 
				one, we can't load other savegames from the original. The way the original 
				saved processes prevents us from loading them, only the initial savegame has 
				no processes running.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="save_compat">
			<header>Do <Pent/> savegames work on all operating systems?</header>
			<body><para>
				Yes. <Pent/> savegames are compatible between all supported operating systems. For 
				example a game saved on Mac OS X works on Windows XP as well.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="obtain_u8">
			<header>Where can I obtain a copy of Ultima 8?</header>
			<body><para>
				If you do not already own a legal copy
				of Ultima 8, the <Pent/> team highly
				suggests you buy a copy. We suggest
				searching for Ultima 8 on sites such as
				Ebay or used software sites. Stores
				which sell used games are often
				good places to try as well.
			</para><para>
				You also might want to look for the
				Ultima Collection, which contains all
				the previous Ultima games as well.
				It is also typically easier to find
				than Ultima 8 because it was released
				much more recently.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="filthy_pirate">
			<header>Can you give me a copy or tell me where to
				download Ultima 8?</header>
			<body><para>
				No! The <Pent/> team does not and never
				will support piracy.
			</para>	<para>
				Members of the <Pent/> team will likely
				ignore, flame, or even banish you
				to another world where no one has ever
				heard of the Avatar if you ask them for
				a pirated copy of any Ultima.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="poor_justification">
			<header>But isn't Ultima 8 abandonware?</header>
			<body><para>
				No, if an entity still exists to claim
				the rights over a piece of software (EA
				in the case of Ultima 8), and the
				company has not openly given away those
				rights to make the software free, then
				the software does not fall under the
				term abandonware or freeware.
			</para><para>
				Any copies of Ultima 8 you find on the
				Internet that claim to be abandoned or
				free are neither, and downloading them
				will be considered piracy.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="against_piracy">
			<header>Why does the <Pent/> team feel so strongly on
				the issue of piracy?</header>
			<body><para>
				First, we understand the amount of work
				that goes into making a game like
				Ultima 8. If we put ourselves into the
				same position as the original
				programmers and artists, we would be
				against the piracy of our work and feel
				that something has been stolen from us
				directly when piracy occurs.
			</para><para>
				Second, the <Pent/> team does not want
				to alienate any former or current
				members of Origin or EA. Some have been
				helpful in the past in informing us,
				and we have a great deal of respect for
				them. We also wish to avoid any
				possible legal issues which could
				threaten to end the <Pent/> project.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
	</section>
	<section title="Changes to the FAQ">
		<sub name="30102011">
			<header>- 30 October 2011</header>
			<body><para>
				<ref1 target="dl_pent"/>: changed to SVN and added OS X snapshot.<br/>
				<ref1 target="snapshot"/>: same.<br/>
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="19022006">
			<header>- 19 February 2006</header>
			<body><para>
				status updates
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="22052005">
			<header>- 22 May 2005</header>
			<body><para>
				cleaned up some mistakes
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="30112004">
			<header>- 30 November 2004</header>
			<body><ul>
				<li><section_ref target="Introduction Part II"/> 
				added a more serious section</li>
				<li><section_ref target="Ultima 8: Pagan"/> 
				also added a couple of more U8 specific Questions</li>
			</ul></body>
		</sub>		
		<sub name="20062004">
			<header>- 20 June 2004</header>
			<body><para>
				Added questions regarding obtaining
				Ultima 8 and the <Pent/> team's stance
				against piracy.
			</para></body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="19062004">
			<header>- 19 June 2004</header>
			<body><para>
				No changes yet, first xml-generated version
			</para></body>
		</sub>
	</section>
</faqs>
